Aduct DB, an open-source fast embeddible
SQL OLAP database that simplifies the
way developers implement analytics. It
was developed in the Netherlands,
written in C++, and first released in
2019. And the TLDDR is that it's like
SQL light, but for columnar data.
Everybody knows that SQLite is the most
deployed database in the world. And
that's because it runs as a single
binary with no dedicated database
management server process necessary,
allowing it to be embedded almost
anywhere, like the billions of
smartphones around the world. Duct DB is
built on the same philosophy, but
instead of storing data row-wise, it
stores it column-wise. But why does that
matter? Well, you see, storing rows
together is great for transactional
workloads like most apps out there, like
an e-commerce website where you need to
read and write entire records at the
same time, but it's not so great for
high volume time series data commonly
found in analytics and IoT where you
need to read and analyze all the data in
one column across many records. When
storage is optimized for columns, it
opens the door to much faster data
aggregation like calculating an average
in addition to much faster filters and
joins. And DUTDB achieves excellent
performance with massive data sets
thanks to its columnar vectorzed query
execution engine where large batches of
values are processed as vectors in one
operation in parallel. It's already in
use at big companies like Meta, Google,
and Airbnb. And you can get started by
installing it. Then run the duct DB
command from the terminal. And now we
can start inserting data just like any
other SQL database. Then if we want to
read an individual column, we can do so
with a select query. And what's
especially awesome is that if we have
some existing data in a CSV or parquet
file, we can access it directly in a SQL
statement. In addition, we could take
that data then output it to a different
format like JSON or even an HTML table.
That's cool and all, but the real power
of this database is its ability to
perform aggregations when working with
time series data. Like imagine we have a
massive data set of stock prices and
need to calculate things like the
average, max, and min values for the
last day. We can easily achieve that in
a select statement thanks to built-in
aggregate functions. Then use group by
to bucket the data into a specific time
range. But under the hood, we get
excellent performance because unlike SQL
light, which processes data rowby row,
duct DB processes data in vectorized
batches of rows and is multi-threaded by
default, making it an excellent choice
for analytical workloads. This has been
duck DB in 100 seconds. Thanks for
watching and I will see you in the next
one.